All right.
Hello, everybody.
Welcome to CS25
Transformers United.
So this is the sixth
iteration of the course,
which is pretty crazy.
Time certainly flies.
So actually, my friend and
a previous co-instructor,
Dave Garg, he's the one
who started this class
and asked me to join
him pretty early on,
actually during the
first year of my PhD.
As we all know, Artificial
Intelligence, AI,
has pretty much
taken over the world.
It's pretty much part of every
aspect of our lives these days.
And we thought
having a course where
people can hear from experts
who are doing state of the art
research, as well
as investigation
on the architecture behind most
modern AI and machine learning
systems and models
called transformers would
be a good way of
disseminating knowledge
while having people who are
more motivated and interested--
getting people more motivated
and interested into this topic.
So that's what
inspired our class.
And the way our class works
is starting next week,
we'll have a speaker, either
from academia or industry,
who will come in to
talk about the work
they're doing with transformers.
And we typically have
a very diverse set
of speakers covering different
topics, transformers applied
to computer vision, text
language modeling, biology,
neuroscience, and so forth.
So definitely look
forward to that.
And so this will be our
first introductory lecture
where we'll go over
course logistics as well
as a background on transformers
and a lot of things
related to them, including
what's coming next, potentially.
Yeah.
So my name is Steven.
I'm a fourth year computer
science PhD student here.
Previously, I was at
Carnegie Mellon & UWaterloo.
And overall, my
research interests
broadly hover around
machine learning,
specifically Natural
Language Processing, NLP.
So I do a lot of things
related to language
models and these days as
well interdisciplinary work
with cognitive science
and psychology.
So I'm looking at things
like efficient reasoning
with small language models in
data limited regimes, human
and cognitively inspired
learning signals for our models,
as well as evaluation
methods and so forth.
Hello, everyone, and welcome.
I'm Karan, the
other co-instructor.
I'm a third year electrical
engineering PhD student.
I also do some work in
language models and efficiency,
so stuff like curriculum
learning and RAG recently.
Though, my main research
interest for the past few years
have been in computer vision
and recently neuroscience.
So my current research
focuses on foundation models
for neuroimaging like fMRI.
Previously, I did my undergrad
at Cal Poly SLO, and for a year,
I was a post-baccalaureate
researcher in Stanford Radiology
before starting my PhD.
And this iteration
of the course is
sponsored by model AGI
House as well as MongoDB.
So we are very grateful
for their support
in order to keep
this class running.
And AGI House and MongoDB
wanted me to communicate
some information.
So they're partnering together
to give students, all of you,
additional direct access to
top founders and researchers
in the AI community through
the Frontier Lunch Club.
So later this
month, there's going
to be an opportunity
for interested students
to have dinner with a handful
of top founders and researchers.
And later in the year, there'll
also be a second event with
a $1,000 project prize.
And these details will be
announced at the dinner.
Additionally, members will
get added to the AGI House's
recruiting pipeline.
So you'll have access to a lot
of startups as well as companies
for both internship as well
as full-time opportunities.
It's an application-based
process, but free to join,
but spots are limited.
Please scan the
QR code to apply.
And there'll be a WhatsApp
group that you guys
will be added to which will
have more details about this.
So of course, most of the
information about our course
will be communicated
through our course website.
Additionally, we have a
mailing list as well as
a Discord server.
So please join those to get the
most up-to-date information.
So lectures are Thursdays
at this time here as well as
on Zoom.
And the only homework
is basically attendance.
In-person attendance is required
when the speaker is in-person,
which is typically the case.
Otherwise, please attend
over Zoom at the very least.
Everyone's allowed three
unexcused absences,
and we track attendance using a
Google form which will be open
as the lecture is running.
So please fill
that in each week.
And please ask questions during
and after the presentation,
either in Zoom chat or use
Slido for the folks online.
Please do not unmute yourself
on Zoom, unless we allow you to.
And for people in person,
just raise your hands
to ask questions.
As I said, there's a Discord
server, a Zoom live stream.
And all lectures
will be recorded.
And the recordings
will be released
on YouTube approximately two
to three weeks afterwards.
We have social events and
potential one-on-one networking
with speakers, so keep
your eye out for that.
And yeah, in-person questions,
please raise your hand,
and we'll get to you.
For the folks on Zoom, again,
please do not unmute yourself.
Any questions or concerns,
please send them in chat.
And anybody auditing in-person
who's not officially enrolled,
if seats are not
available, please
give priority to the
students who are enrolled.
And please keep
behavior appropriate.
So what we hope that
you'll take away
from this course is a better
understanding of how exactly
transformers work, from
attention to scaling
and so forth as well as
learning more about cutting edge
applications in various,
different domains,
as well, of course,
live exposure
to frontier research speakers
who are shaping the field.
And yeah, things
like key limitations,
open problems that
hopefully you guys
will be able to
contribute to as well
in order to further improve
our AI models and systems.
All right.
So to start, I'll give
a very brief overview
of transformers, what they are.
It's the title of the course, of
course, and also the direction
that the field has taken
to get up to transformers.
So early ML around
pre-2012, most work
consisted of some of
hand-engineered features
relevant to the task at
hand, maybe classification
or some other thing.
These were passed into
shallow models which
then were trained
to make predictions
based on these features.
And in order to
train your models,
you had a generally smallish
set of expensive labels that
were collected by hand that you
compared the model's predictions
to make a feedback
loop that allowed
you to update the parameters.
Then we gradually had a move
to supervise deep learning,
so replacing the hand-engineered
features as the models
got bigger with raw
data, so the data
that was used to
generate the features.
And in this way, you went
directly from the raw data
to the predictions,
taking out that middleman
step of hand engineering.
Going further, we move to
self-supervised learning.
So here, we thought even
having these expensive labels
was too much.
And so models were
trained here by corrupting
the raw data in some way,
maybe noising, or masking,
or that sort of thing, and
then training the model
to reconstruct the
original uncorrupted data.
And from this, you learned very
general raw representations
that could be applied to a
variety of downstream tasks.
So after this, you could
use your model and fine
tune it to do whatever
task you wanted it to.
As a case study of language,
a lot of early work
was like sentiment analysis, so
taking in short pieces of text,
say, reviews, and just trying
to classify whether they're
positive, neutral, or negative.
So here you also had
features based on the words.
And of course, your
classification task
was pretty simple, just
say 0, 1, 2 classification.
Later, similarly to the
direction I described,
we moved to going a
bit more to the source.
So language is, of course, very
sequential and context rich.
If I give you a random sentence
like the quick brown fox
jumps over the,
you'll know what comes
next because you've seen
that sentence so many times
in your life.
So similarly, we started
training language models
to do next token prediction.
This also allowed you to make
maximum use of raw text data
because you could generate
a very large amount of pairs
like this.
And you might have guessed,
vision was no different.
Directions were pretty
similar, so things
like autoencoders to try to
generate those representations
that could be applied
downstream, and also
things like
contrastive learning,
which we'll talk about later.
With vision, one
recentish architecture
is the masked autoencoder.
So the same idea I
described, except in vision,
where you mask out
some part of the image
and train the model to
reconstruct those missing
pieces.
One interesting question here
is how do you do the masking.
Typically, it's done randomly.
However, you could
have a random mask
that reveals three
patches like this, which
makes the problem very easy.
Even a human could tell or
these other three patches, which
makes the problem very hard.
So one future
direction is to find
a better balance between these.
Going back to language, a key
component of language models
is word embeddings.
So we understand language
pretty naturally,
but models work in numbers.
So in order to bridge this
gap, you need dense vectors
in a high dimensional
space that allow
you to represent all the
words in the vocabulary.
Typical methods in this space
are like Word2Vec, GloVe,
and FastTex, which you
can look at in case
you haven't come across them.
And these enable things like
arithmetic and, of course,
learning in this space.
For instance,
semantic similarity,
if you take king
minus man plus woman,
you're embedding should
roughly give you queen, which
is the analogous word there.
However, static
embeddings in which
you assign a single vector to
one word have some limitations.
For instance, bank as
a financial institution
and a river bank would
get the same vector,
even though their meanings
are completely different.
So to solve this
problem, there are
things like
contextual embeddings
which consider the
surrounding context
to assign different
vectors to the same word.
Moving a bit closer
to transformers,
we got to RNNs, Recurrent
Neural Networks.
And these are sequence
models that process inputs
step by step while maintaining
a memory or hidden state.
So you take your input, you
do some operations on it,
you put some information in
memory and some information
to the output.
You can repeat this over
time to get a sequence.
However, these suffer
from some problems,
like if your sequence
is very long,
you're going to forget what you
learned at the very first step.
So Long, Short Term
Memory Networks or LSTMs
are a gated variant
of RNNs that aim
to solve this problem
by better preserving
long-range dependencies.
So here you add a
couple more parameters
that better govern when you
should remember or forget
something and when you
should output something.
So then we get to transformers.
I'll give a very quick overview.
So self-attention learns what
to focus on for each token.
So if we have a
sequence, the connections
between different words might
be more or less important.
So self-attention learns some
matrices, query, key, and value
that allow you to learn
these relationships.
To give an analogy for these,
make it a little less abstract,
imagine you're looking
for a book in a library.
Each one has a summary, a key
that tells you what it's about.
Once you find a match between
what you're looking for
or your query, and
the summary, you
can access the book to, well,
get its information, the values.
And in attention, we do this
across, say, all the books
in the library and
do a soft matching
to get the book that
is most relevant.
So you'd get a score for
every book telling you
how relevant it is.
And self-attention is
just this technique
applied to a single sequence.
So you learn connections between
every word in a sentence,
say, to every other
word in that sentence.
One issue here is
that models that
just do this have no
notion of ordering.
So to get around this, we
add positional encodings
or positional embeddings which
just tell the model where
it's looking for each word.
So it's a very simple example.
You could just have a
one for the first word,
a two for the
second word, and on,
and your model would then
overtraining, learn to associate
these with the ordering
of the sequence.
And lastly, you can scale this
up, do multi-head attention.
So on the same
sequence, you can have
multiple different
learned attention matrices
or models that together give you
a more detailed representation.
So this is the
full architecture.
I won't get into
too much detail,
but essentially combines
all of the components
that I talked about into a very
well-performing architecture.
So we just talked about RNNs.
Why are those not used
in the latest models?
While transformers are
better for various reasons,
a few here are that they
allow for parallelism.
So RNNs by design are
one step by one step.
So you have to process
sequences in order,
which makes things much slower.
Whereas in attention, you can
process your entire sequence
in one step and speed
this up on GPUs.
Additionally, although LSTMs
solve the vanishing gradients
and forgetting
problem a little bit,
transformers still handle
long contexts much better.
You can scale them
up much better.
So these days, we
have models that
can take in a million
tokens or to that order.
And lastly here,
like I allows you,
like I showed, to access all
previous tokens in the context
and draw connections
in between them
whereas RNNs and
LSTMs are limited
to whatever they can store in
memory in their hidden state.
So with all of these
advancements in architectures,
transformers today have
spread to all areas
of science and technology.
So we have LLMs, which all
of us probably use every day
like GPT-5, Claude, et cetera.
We have many vision models that
are getting better and better,
some even coming to your phone.
We have speech, biology, video,
robotics, and so much more.
Large language
models in particular
are just scaled up transformers.
So the architecture
I showed scaled
to billions of parameters,
incurring heavy computational
costs, like time and GPUs.
However, they perform very well.
Generally, they're
pre-trained on massive amounts
of general text data.
So the internet, to put
it in a simple word,
with the training
objective that I mentioned
of next token prediction, so
given a sequence just predicting
the next word, as you
scale transformers
up as language models, a lot
of emergent abilities come up.
So there's a paper
on this seminal paper
on emergent abilities.
But just by training
on general text data,
you start to be able
to do math or reasoning
or that sort of thing.
And then like I just mentioned,
these large general models
are also very good for a few
shot or zero shot learning.
So you can give it a
completely new task
that it has never seen before.
But just because it's
seen so much data,
it's able to generalize
and very quickly learn
what you want it to do.
So now I'll be talking
about pre-training
and the importance of data.
So pre-training is basically
the first phase of training.
So you have a randomly
initialized model,
and your goal is to get as much
knowledge and basic capabilities
into it as you can.
So typically, this
involves training
on a large variety of
diverse internet text.
Because so much
diverse text means
the model is able to hopefully
learn a statistical distribution
of language that is similar
to the natural distribution
of human language.
And, yeah, the
fundamental aspect,
especially of pre-training,
is in the data.
It's the fuel behind our
machine-learning and AI models,
especially for LLMs that
are trained on so much text.
So how do we maximally leverage
data given its importance?
So we'll be talking about
a few projects here,
ranging from the smaller
scale to the larger scale.
So I'll be talking about
these two small or child scale
language learning projects.
And Karan we'll be talking
more about some larger scale
projects involving
things like RAG
considered pre-training
and curriculum learning.
So I'll begin by talking
about small language
models and BabyLM.
So humans and neural
networks, language models,
learn fundamentally differently.
Like I said, language
models are typically
trained on large amounts
of internet text.
They learn from predicting the
next token with the highest
probability, given all the
previous ones, whereas humans
likely learn in a more
structured, hierarchical ways.
For example, we are more
goal-based, goal-driven,
and our language is
decomposed, given
goals or steps that we want to
take to accomplish something.
Furthermore, we learn in
a more interactive manner.
So we talk to other people.
So as children growing up, we
talk to other kids, our mom,
babysitter, and so forth.
Whereas, again,
language models are
trained on just pure
text on the internet.
Furthermore, we're
multimodal and sensory.
We're continuously absorbing
information from the world,
and this grounds our
learning of language.
Whereas most language
models are simply text only.
And our focus of the two
projects I'll be talking about
are mainly the language
data differences
between human learning and
language model learning.
So why study small
models and data?
Why not just use the biggest
models that can do everything?
Well, firstly,
computational costs.
Not everybody can train a model
like OpenAI, GPT-4, GPT-5.
Takes millions of dollars.
Furthermore, small models can
open up more potential use
cases.
You can use it on your phone to
do things on your everyday life.
That might be much more of
aligned to your goals or tasks
compared to an open source, so
a closed source large language
model like GPT-5.
And one other thing is
techniques discovered
at the small scale
can potentially
be applied to larger scales
to improve their efficiency
and capabilities as well.
And lastly, a
greater understanding
of how we can make small
language models more effective
might also lead to
greater understanding
of the cognitive models of how
humans actually learn language
so efficiently.
So the first project
I'll be talking about
is a recent paper we just
worked on called baby scale:
investigating models trained on
individual children's language
input.
So human children, again,
learn from far less data
than large language
models, magnitudes less.
A human child from
the ages of 0 to 13
is exposed to approximately 10
to 100 million words of language
data, compared to large
language models in order
to achieve similar capabilities
such as generalization,
abstraction, and reasoning.
So we wanted to ask, why
exactly is this the case?
And thankfully,
we had a data set
that actually had transcripts of
individual children's language
data.
So we were wondering, could
we train language models
on the actual transcript data
that individual children are
exposed to and what
they say as well,
and see how that might
scale, as well as
how performance might vary
across individual families,
and also to look
at what properties
of the actual data, language
data that children are exposed
to might make them
more effective
learners compared to others?
So what we saw--
so on the left actually is
a scaling plot across four
different benchmarks.
So Zorro tests grammaticality
and linguistic abilities.
WS is Word Similarity.
So WS and comms test
semantic understanding.
And EWoK tests general
basic world knowledge.
So you see the four
graphs on the left
are trained on our
individual family models.
So you see there's quite
a lot of variation,
but there is some
positive scaling.
So even at such extremely
small or tiny scales of data,
there is scaling with
the quantity of data.
There is positive trends, but
the signal is quite noisy.
And you'll see the performance
varies quite heavily
between the individual models
trained on different families
data.
So on the right, we trained on
synthetic, tiny dialogues data.
So this is a larger data
up to 200 million tokens.
And it's synthetic and cleaner.
So you'll see with this cleaner
more synthetic controlled
data, the scaling laws are
cleaner and hold better there.
So if we were to extrapolate and
look at broader scaling curves,
so up to Roberta base, which
was pre-trained on, I believe,
around $20 or $30
billion tokens,
you'll see that our smaller
experiments do lie along
the broader scaling curves.
So again, I said, the scaling--
one other thing I
forgot to mention
is the scaling does
depend on the task.
So it scaled better for
Zorro or grammaticality
compared to a moral
knowledge, for example.
So it shows that individual
children's learning
environments, at least when
training language models,
might not be enough to get
general basic world model
a world understanding,
and you might
need more extraneous or external
data in order to achieve that.
And the other
takeaways I discussed.
Furthermore, we conducted
a very comprehensive
linguistic analysis of these
individual families training
data, comparing--
correlating them to the final
performance of the models
trained on their data.
And we found that it wasn't
just data scale that mattered,
but a lot of other
qualities, for example,
things related to semantic
diversity and the number
of conversations, the
distributional divergence
among the different individual
data sets of each family,
and so forth.
So overall, we found that
better performing data sets
tended to be more structured and
more diverse and richer in terms
of interaction and
coverage diversity.
So this lines up
with child language
of research, emphasizing
that quality really
matters more than just quantity,
especially at such small scales.
So overall, child
scale language model
learning on such extremely
limited amounts of data
is possible.
But it's quite
task-dependent, and it really
depends on the quality as
well as the other aspects
of your data, more
than the amount
of data at such small scales.
And studying child
scale data in general
might allow us to build
more capable and efficient
small language
models and possibly
also allow us to
understand human language
acquisition better.
So the second project
I'll be talking about
is also at smaller
scales, but it's
investigating training bilingual
or multilingual small language
models.
So in particular, this is
a thing called a fusion
hypothesis, mainly
applying to humans, which
is a hypothesis that human
children that grow up
in multilingual
environments might actually
suffer more or have more
difficulties learning,
since they're constantly
required to balance or take
in so much different
conflict information
from different languages,
and this might actually
decrease their
capabilities of learning,
a single primary language.
So we're wondering, do
these things actually
apply, especially
for language models?
And secondly, we're wondering
if the exact exposure structure
or the way that this bilingual
language is expressed
to the model or the child,
does this affect performance?
And thirdly, do these
effects vary with things
like the model and data size?
So in order to do
so, we constructed
these different
types of data sets.
So we have some top lines, which
are hundreds million tokens
of English and Spanish data.
And then we have
some baseline models,
which are half of this
in terms of English only.
And then on top of this,
we added multilingual data
in a second language,
Spanish in this case.
So it's 100 million tokens
mixed 50 million of English
and 50 million of Spanish.
And this is
simultaneously learned.
We're not training on 50 million
English and then 50 million
Spanish, but rather, there's
100 million tokens together.
And we also look
at code switching,
which is the interleaving of the
two different languages at both
a sentence, as well
as a word level
and how that might
affect learning.
So in terms of the
first research question,
we found that the perplexities
of the multilingual model
are low in both languages
and very comparable, even
very slightly lower than
the English baseline,
showing that adding
a second language
doesn't really affect
too much behavior
or learning of the
first language.
And this is also shown
through our benchmarks
the multilingual models
perform pretty on par
across different seeds compared
to the English-only models.
And secondly, again, we looked
at different exposure schemes.
For example, should
having the mom always talk
in English and dad
always talk in Spanish
versus having them be random by
Speaker and so forth, as well
as sentence versus word
level code switching?
And again, we found no
significant differences here.
And thirdly, we looked
at how these effects
may vary with scale.
So we found that
using a smaller model
didn't really
affect performance,
whereas dropping
down all the way
down to 20 million words
instead of 100 million words
did significantly
affect performance.
But overall, our
trends held up there.
So overall, we find
there's no interference.
So training small language
models on, for example,
two languages doesn't really
impact or negatively affect
the performance on a single
language, which is quite cool.
Further, the exposure structure
is surprisingly irrelevant.
It doesn't really matter how
exactly you interleave the two
languages.
It doesn't really degrade
learning of the models.
And data scale matters
more than model scale
for multilingual
learning at this size.
So those are the
overall takeaways.
And feel free to
check out the paper.
Next I'll be
talking a little bit
about work in retrieval
augmented generation.
So firstly, what is Retrieval
Augmented Generation or RAG?
So typically, like we
described, in language models,
you just have this
large set of web data.
You train your LLM to model that
data and go from user queries
to outputs.
In RAG, we augment the
system a little bit
by adding some specific
or domain knowledge
documents with a retriever.
Whenever you get a user
query, your retriever
picks out of this large set of
documents the most relevant ones
and feeds them to
the LLMs context,
which it can then use to improve
the outputs that it generates.
So one of our works was
studying RAG scaling.
So how much RAG should you use?
If you have a fixed set of,
say, hundreds billion tokens,
what allocations should you
do for both of those things?
And if you plotted
retrieval tokens
in the middle versus
pre-training tokens,
for every budget, there would
be some optimal, which would
form this optimal frontier.
A very quick overview of
the results, on the right,
we found that small models
benefit much more from RAG.
So as you scale up
RAG, their performance
improves, whereas larger
models saturate very quickly.
So described in figure form,
if we plot pre-training tokens
saved per retrieval token--
so essentially, we're
looking at how much
pre-training does it
take to match the performance
gain from retrieval or vice
versa?
And when looking at
this, we found that there
was this crossover point.
So there's a minimum
amount of pre-training
that you need to do in order for
your model to effectively use
any RAG that you give it.
And this occurs for us at
about four pre-training tokens
per parameter.
So if you have a 1
billion parameter model,
you need about 4 billion
tokens to reach that point.
Also on the right, we
found that the improvement
per 1 billion
retrieval tokens varied
by the scale of the model.
So a very small model,
like 30 million parameters,
benefits much more
from RAG compared
to a large model like 3
billion parameters, which
would sufficient pre-training
almost has zero benefit.
It's going down on the
graph, as you can see.
This also makes sense because
a large model is already
memorized so much information
that it can't really
use RAG with general web data.
However, of course, if you
had domain specific documents,
then that would be
a different story.
Very quick overview
of this project,
but if this seems interesting
to you, you can scan this QR.
Oops.
Next I'll talk a
bit about curriculum
learning approaches and
scaling up models using this.
So like Steven
was talking about,
as the cost of
pre-training grows,
there is more interest in
improving learning efficiency
and trying to train models with
less than a trillion tokens
or the insane scales
that are used these days.
And also typical pre-training
differs significantly
from how we learn, and also
can result in small models
that struggle at reasoning.
So how can we
bridge these scales.
One idea I had was we as humans
learn from curriculum in school.
Alongside that,
however, our brains
are also growing
physically in size.
So can we do the same
thing for language models,
start with a small model
and very simple data
and scale up both
things in tandem,
so growing the model as
the data gets harder.
Some prior work in this space
has been like synthetic data
sets like Steven
used tiny dialogues,
there's also tiny stories.
So very simple, like
five-year-old level stories.
There's some work in
data filtering as well.
So on that quality end,
curating large data
sets that are deduplicated
and very clean.
On the model growing end, there
is some prior work in stacking.
So if we take a small model,
train it on whatever amount
of data and then copy
the encoder layers
and train further, does
that improve performance?
And this other paper,
Midas, from 2024
showed that when you
do this stacking,
layers that are
next to each other
essentially learn
the same things.
So they're not
very useful, which
motivates new or better
approaches to doing
this stacking or model growth.
So what we came up with
was, like I mentioned,
starting off with
small model, say,
half the model size and
relatively easy data,
training it a little
bit, and gradually
adding layers as you go
throughout training until you
reach your final
model size, which you
can train on your hardest
data to do the tasks
that you want to.
And we found that doing
this approach, which
we call CGLS, Curriculum
Guided Layer Scaling,
you do achieve better
performance than just
training randomly your largest
model size on all of your data
or even using the
same curriculum,
so a easy to hard scaling,
but at the largest model
size train ones.
And these results also scale up.
So if we move from 2 billion
to 20 billion tokens,
the gap in performance
gets even larger,
so the model gets better.
So as a TLDR, testing at these
124 million parameter and 1B
scales, combining model growth
with a structured curriculum
allows you to unlock the
benefits of model growth
or stacking techniques.
But not all tasks benefited
equally from this approach
and curriculum.
And although I didn't show it
here at 1 billion parameter
scale, the perplexity
of the random baseline
was better than
that of the CGLS 1,
despite the CGLS 1 being
better at reasoning tasks.
And there's, of course, a lot of
future potential in this space,
like tuning
hyperparameters further,
exploring other
notions of curriculum.
So maybe what we
think is easy or hard
might not be easy or
hard for language model
and applying this to
other domains like image
or medical imaging
and that thing.
And like the other one's, paper,
if you'd like to check it out.
Yeah.
So now we'll talk about some
of these overall takeaways
from these four projects,
studying data, especially
for pre-training.
So overall, we see that data
effectiveness is not just
the volume and quantity of data,
but the quality, structure,
and how exactly it's used.
So data selection and how you
actually use it strategically
are very important
considerations.
So we saw with the
baby scale project
that individual environments
of children's learning
vary, and the differences are
driven more by data composition
and quality than quantity.
And with the
bilingual project, we
saw that models can, too,
learn two languages effectively
without confusion or detriment
to the first language,
regardless of how it's exposed
to those two languages.
Third, with the curriculum
guided on their scaling project
that Karan just
talked about, we saw
that scaling your model
alongside a data curriculum
improves downstream
performance up to the 1 billion
parameter scale.
And with the right considerate
pre-training scaling laws
project, we saw that
the optimal performance
comes from balancing
parametric learning
through pre-training
and external memory
through retrieval.
So now, so the overall takeaway
is that all of this research
underscores that effective
language modeling isn't just
amassing large amounts of data,
but smarter data utilization
strategies that can
really effectively harness
its structure, quality,
and characteristics.
And by continuing to
refine and explore
these data-centric approaches,
especially for pre-training,
the future of LLM
training promises
smarter, more efficient,
and adaptable models.
Now, we're going to get to
the second major topic, which
is post-training.
So after we've
effectively pre-trained
a randomly initialized
model, for example,
on a lot of internet data, and
it has basic capabilities, what
now?
How do we adapt it to specific
task, scenarios, users, domains,
and et cetera?
So this is exactly what
post-training looks at.
So there's many strategies,
like fine-tuning,
prompt-based techniques,
and what Karan somewhat
talked about, retrieval-based
approaches, like RAG.
So there's a major of inference
time-based approach called
chain of thought prompting.
So this is when
you want the model,
for example, to talk to you
or to answer a question,
instead of outputting
the answer directly,
you get it to actually think
step by step like a human
before answering a question.
So, for example, we decompose
more difficult problems
like math questions into
smaller subproblems or steps.
And that's how we reason
through them and solve them.
And this paper chain
of thought reasoning
basically finds that you
can do the same thing
with language models.
This suggests that deep
in the model's weights,
it knows more about
the problem than it's
letting on when you just prompt
it to give you the answer.
So here's just an example.
You have a basic math problem.
Standard prompting
directly gives you
the answer, whereas
chain of thought
has the model actually think
and output its reasoning
steps before it generates
the final answer conditioned
on these reasoning steps.
Now, there's been
different works
that extend chain of
thought, for example,
to tree of thoughts.
So rather than a
single reasoning path,
the model considers
multiple reasoning paths
and actually evaluates which one
is more effective, for example,
using methods like
majority vote and so forth.
Furthermore, you can offload
your intermediate reasoning
steps to other tools or
things like programs.
For example, you
can generate code
as intermediate reasoning
steps, which can then
be used to help solve
them, for example, using
Python or some other coding
language or interpreter.
And this helps provide a more
precise reasoning steps as well
as final answers leading
to higher performance,
especially on things like,
for example, mathematics.
Furthermore, like
I said, typically,
when there's a
very hard problem,
we would want to decompose
them into smaller,
easier subproblems.
And that's exactly what
socratic questioning does.
So it uses a
self-questioning module
to use the language model to
propose subproblems related
to the original problem.
And then it uses a divide
and conquer algorithm
to solve these subproblems
recursively, and then
get an answer to your
overall original problem.
There's also other
works that look
at things like decomposing--
formulating compositional
tasks as computation graphs.
Again, this is similar
to breaking things up
into subprocedures
or subproblems.
And next, there's another line
of post-training approaches
which use reinforcement
learning and rewards.
So the most common
is reinforcement
learning with human feedback.
So this is a technique that
trains a reward model directly
from human feedback.
For example, if you have
two different responses
that a model gives, you
give this to a human
and get them to rank or
choose which response
they prefer over
the other, and this
can be used as a reward in
order to post train your model
to be more effective.
Furthermore, one
innovation is it's
called DPO or Direct
Preference Optimization.
So this is a RL-free
based approach.
So it directly trains the model
to prefer human outputs in order
to rank higher without requiring
a separate reward model.
So this is a pretty
popular approach.
And then humans,
though, humans are
subjective and biased
as well as the fact
that they're typically costly.
If you need a bunch
of humans to rank
thousands or millions
of outputs, for example,
that can be infeasible.
So another work does
this with AI, actually.
So it gets AI off the
shelf LLMs in order
to give their
preferences for which
answers they prefer over
others, for example,
and uses this in order
to tune the outputs.
And then DeepSeek came up with
GRPO or Group Relative Policy
Optimization.
So rather than simply binary
ranking responses of which one
they prefer over the
other, this actually
ranks responses in a group using
multiple different responses.
This provides richer, more
fine-grained feedback,
which has shown to
improve performance
on many tasks such
as mathematics.
And then the last part I
want to touch upon here
for reinforcement learning is
process supervision or process
rewards.
So again, a lot of
problems or a lot
of tasks that you want a
language model, or robot,
or whatever to solve
involve multiple steps.
So rather than only having
a reward at the end,
it might be more
optimal to actually give
intermediate reward
signals to your model.
So this is exactly what
process supervision is.
So you label or evaluate
intermediate reasoning steps,
and then you train
models in order
to more effectively produce
good reasoning traces.
So the individual steps
are more accurate,
which leads to, of course,
a better final answer
but also better
overall reasoning
behavior and performance.
And this also reduces
things like reward-hacking
and so forth.
Next, in a similar vein,
I'll talk about AI agents
and specifically
self-improvement.
So what is an AI agent?
You've probably used one, Cloud
Code or that sort of thing.
So it's just a system that
perceives its environment,
makes some of decisions,
like this chain of thought,
and then takes actions towards
achieving the goal that
is generally given by a
human, so like you telling
Cloud Code to build an app.
One big benefit of agents
is that they can reflect
and improve upon themselves.
So the loop looks
something like this.
When given an input
query, the agent
can gather all of its
inputs, the query,
any other environmental factors
that might need to consider,
can reason, plan,
and decide what
it wants to build or do,
take action, and then observe
what happened.
So if you've ever
used Cloud Code,
you might find that
it runs the script
and sees if it compiled
successfully before reflecting
and if needed, repeating the
same loop to update its outputs.
So in this way, models can
currently self-improve.
They can reflect
on their own output
and try to iteratively
improve those outputs.
Let's just skip that.
So, yeah, models-- and this
way learn from past mistakes
and adjust their
future responses
based on their prior failures.
Another thing that you can
do is have a memory store,
so like GPT these days,
store some memory.
And this way it can also
store its past mistakes
and try to adjust the responses
that it gives you later based
on what it learned
from those loops.
And you can combine this as
well with tool use, API calls,
or retrieval like we talked
about to further improve
your agents so it can generate
a reasoning plan, which
may involve calling
an external tool,
running a web search,
database query,
and use all of those
outputs, incorporate them
into its final response.
OK.
So he talked a
lot about language
on how all the
techniques that go
into improving language
models and making them
what they are today.
Next, we'll move a bit onto
applications of transformers
beyond language.
So as we've all probably
seen, there are many,
and AI has basically started
to take over every field.
So there's things like
DeepMind's, AlphaFold,
and genetics, lots
of medical models
or medical language
models, AlphaGo for chess,
et cetera, image generation.
Speaking of image
generation, I'll
talk really quickly about vision
transformers and how they work.
So before vision
transformers, there
were CNNs, Convolutional
Neural Networks.
However, when they
came along and started
yielding very good
performance on language,
people started thinking about
ways to apply them to image.
If you simply took every single
pixel and treated it as a token,
even if you had a very
small 28 by 28 image,
that would still flatten to
almost 1,000 pixels or tokens.
And this is pretty expensive
even for today's hardware
abilities.
Hence, this paper or
vision transformer
suggested breaking down
the images into patches
and coding these patches
into smaller sequences
that a transformer
could learn from.
And this worked very
well for various tasks,
like I touched on towards
the beginning, served
as a very good representation
learning algorithm as well.
However, if CNNs work so well
and work so well for many years,
why use transformers?
A couple of things.
Transformers are very
flexible architectures
with minimal inductive
priors, so they
make very few assumptions
about the input data.
In contrast, CNNs assume
that nearby pixels
are related on locality in
that they process images
with filters.
So you might have a
4 by 4 filter, which
is assuming that, that scale
has relations inside of it.
These assumptions help
CNNs learn effectively
with limited training
data, however, also
bottlenecked their performance.
Transformers, on
the other hand, have
to learn from very
large data sets,
so you can't really train
on the same scale as CNNs.
However, they make
no assumptions
and can therefore learn much
better on these larger data
sets.
Another big shift in
the field was CLIP.
So trying to align
text representations
with image representations.
And they did this pretty
simply and intuitively
in that you encode your
text into a vector,
you encode your image into a
vector through separate models,
and then update
these models to try
to align both through paired
data for images and text.
So one application that
this thing that I work on
is in neuroscience,
transformers for neuroscience.
So with fMRI, we can capture
changes in blood oxygenation
across the brain.
However, these are very
noisy signals and also
very high dimensional
and more so correlated
fluctuations than really robust
activations, like a deep brain
electrode might give you.
Therefore, what
generally matters
isn't the absolute
values of the signals,
but rather the correlations
in between them.
So one line of
work in this field
was to try to cluster the
different parts of the brain
into networks.
And they found that
certain numbers of networks
were more stable than others,
and they settled on 7 and 17.
So if we decompose your brain
into seven broad networks,
we get a hierarchy that looks
like your visual center, so
processing vision,
things like salience,
which regulates attention
and your senses,
and the DMN, which
is like daydreaming.
So if you want to apply
transformers to this data,
one thing you could
do very simply
is to just train with
random masking on the data.
And this works OK
at large scales.
However, we wanted to make
a more interpretable better
architecture.
So we took this notion
of dividing the brain up
into networks and gave this
to the model as a prior.
So instead of predicting
random patches masked out
throughout the brain, we
mask out an entire network,
say, all the information
in your visual center,
and see if the model can predict
that given the information
in the rest of your brain.
This allows us to learn
more robust embeddings that
give us insights into diseases,
like Alzheimer's disease.
So on the left,
bottom left, you can
see that the embeddings
trained from this model cluster
based on disease
status, so CNS control--
MCI is Mild Cognitive
Impairment--
which eventually generally
leads in old age to Alzheimer's
disease if one is prone to it.
Additionally, with
this architecture,
we can probe dependencies
between different parts
of the brain.
So how connected is
your visual system, say,
your daydreaming network?
And with this, we
get pretty plots
like this, which show
us all the connections
in between different parts
of the brain, and also
how predictable each
network is based
on the information in
the rest of the brain.
So we see that
your visual center
is pretty predictable from
the rest of your brain,
whereas others, like subcortical
regions involved in memory
are more separate.
You can't really predict them
from the rest of the brain.
Also since we have data from
multiple different groups,
including those with
Alzheimer's disease,
we can see where changes
happen inside the brain.
So we find that the DNN
or Daydreaming Network
is disproportionately
affected compared
to the rest of the brain.
So this might help influence,
say, drug development
or give us more mechanistic
knowledge into how
the disease progresses.
And if you find this
work interesting,
can read the paper as well.
So a very different
application of transformers
to medical imaging.
So the future, what's next?
We've seen that transformers
have pretty much pervaded
into all of our lives.
So however, they can still
label a lot more applications.
So increasingly, we have domain
specific foundation models
and medicine and law, cetera,
and also increasingly getting
integrated into the real world
with personalized education
in some countries,
advancing health,
taking load off doctors,
and more fun applications
as well, like interactive
entertainment and gaming,
having your NPC talk
to you as an AI.
However, there are still many
missing ingredients to AGI
or what we're all chasing.
A few are memory.
So models right now still
have very limited memory
unlike humans, which
have fast recall
and can access
very large stores.
So to fix these
things, we also have
to reduce computational
complexity.
It's not very
sustainable to train
on trillions of tokens with
trillions of parameters,
and also things like allowing
models to self-improve further
beyond what agents can do.
So actually update
their parameters
and get better at
tasks as they come
across them, more
autonomy and long horizon
decision making as well.
And throughout all of
this, we have to make sure
to try to align them with
emotional intelligence
and social understanding,
align them with our values
so they don't treat
us as adversaries.
There is also a direction of
minifying models on device LLMs,
like we talked about.
So if we can make smaller
models much better,
we can run them
on, say, our phones
and have similar performance or
help us more with daily tasks.
And in the future, we may even
be able to fine tune models
locally.
And in a similar vein, there
are many limits to scaling.
So going up in data
size or model size,
already there are diminishing
returns from scaling alone.
Training on web
data, as we do today,
probably won't get us to AGI.
So there are shifts to more
post-training methods like we
talked about, RLHF or RLAIF,
improving data quality,
so curriculums, maybe trying
to see how humans learn
and Steven's work.
However, another risk of all
these post-training techniques
like RLHF is that if
you train the model
too much in
post-training, it might
forget what it learned
in pre-training
and get worse on the
task rather than better.
So still ongoing work to try to
break through this scaling law
limit.
And this might happen through
new architectures, higher
quality data, improve
training procedures,
and like I mentioned,
also making
smaller models more advanced.
Yeah.
Great.
So there's still a lot
of remaining weaknesses
or challenges.
So Karan touched upon
reaching limits with scaling.
I'm trying to get these
models more computationally
efficient so we can
run them on our phone.
We can maybe even train them
on our phones in the future
and so forth.
Another big issue that remains,
especially in language models,
but models in general, it's
this thing called hallucination.
So what is hallucination?
We typically think
of this as when
a language model, for example,
provides false or incorrect
information, it'll make up
things, facts, citations,
details that don't exist,
but also usually sound
quite confident about it.
It fails to reflect uncertainty
when the knowledge is missing.
It doesn't really
know what to say.
I don't know.
But it tries to always--
it pretends like it
knows everything, basically.
So why this happens, there's
a few potential explanations.
One is models optimized for
plausibility and not truth.
They're trained to predict
or produce the next token
with the highest probability.
So this is not
necessarily true text.
It's just the most
probable text.
There's also a
lack of grounding.
So this relates to what I'll
talk about later, world models.
But language models,
they don't really
have notion of the world
or external grounding.
And further, a lot of the times
when users talk to models,
they're ambiguous
or they give prompts
that don't have
enough information.
So then this can
confuse the model,
for example, which
prompts it to then produce
hallucinated information.
So again, hallucination
reduces things
like trust and reliability.
And especially in high stakes
domains like law and health
care, you don't want to
rely on a model that's
just saying whatever,
things that are incorrect.
And furthermore, a lot of
times it's hard to detect.
Again, because the
model sounds confident,
so how can you be sure if
it's hallucinating or not?
Furthermore, not all errors are
hallucinations, and what is true
depends on the context as well.
So these are things
I'll touch upon.
But overall, there's
a thing missing.
What exactly is a hallucination?
We still don't have a concrete
or unified definition.
So this is one of our
recent works looks at,
which is we actually
define a unified definition
of hallucination.
So again, existing
definitions are different.
It depends on things like the
field or the task at hand.
For example, in
summarization, a hallucination
means when the language model
produces an output which is not
faithful to the source document,
whereas an open domain QA,
it means it produces a factually
incorrect response, something
that is not true
in the real world.
And in the case of
agents, hallucination
means, for example, when it
might take incorrect actions
based on, for
example, hallucinating
a button on the web page that
doesn't exist and so forth.
So the same output can be a
hallucination in one setting,
but correct in another.
So our core idea is that
hallucination is basically
about world models.
So your large language
model or whatever model
has learned a
internal world model
through things like
pre-training or training
on large amounts of data.
On the other hand, when
you have a task at hand,
you have an external or ground
truth reference world model.
For example, this
is a world model
that is described by
your source document
when it comes to summarization.
And this world model,
on the other hand,
is the real world itself when it
comes to things open domain QA.
So this world that the
language model learned
may match this reference world
model or may contradict it.
So hallucination occurs when
the model's learned world model
is it contradicts what is the
reference or the ground truth
world model.
So it's not just about
producing a wrong answer,
but having wrong beliefs
about the world itself.
So in general, we
define hallucination
as a world modeling error.
So we break this down into
structured mathematical
framework.
So every hallucination
depends on three things.
Like I said, a reference
world model which defines what
is actually true.
For example, this can be
a document, a database,
the real world, and
so forth, depending
on the context and situation.
You also have a view.
So this is what the
model can actually see.
For example, information that
it has retrieved from a database
is part of its view.
And then you have
a conflict policy.
So when you have different
sources of information
that may disagree, you need
a way of resolving conflicts.
For example, we know
in the real world
that Harry Potter is a boy.
But, for example, in
a specific situation,
a Harry Potter might be a girl.
And, for example, when
someone is role playing
or they're making
up their own story,
the user, so in
that case, the model
should align with
what the user thinks
is true, which is that
Harry Potter is a girl.
So you need a way of
resolving these conflicts
when sources disagree.
So a hallucination is when
a model outputs something
that contains a
claim that is false
given these three components.
So this is a unified
definition because we
found that pretty much
all existing hallucination
definitions and cases
of hallucination
and different tasks
and situations
can all be put under
this framework.
For example, in summarization,
again, our reference world
is the source document.
What the model sees, its
view is this document,
and our conflict policy is
the document is the truth.
It doesn't matter what is in
the real world and so forth,
but the document is
your source of truth.
And a hallucination type is
an intrinsic contradiction
where the language
model produces
an output, which contains
a claim which contradicts
the source document.
On the other hand, for
example, for agents, this
is when the environment, the web
page is exposed to is the truth,
and the agent
hallucinates in that it
thinks its environment is
different from what it actually
is.
So our unified definition
allows for this encompassing
of all the prior different
definitions and domain
and tasks.
This also allows us to
separate different errors.
Having a grounded
definition like ours--
for example, hallucination means
a wrong belief about the world--
separates it from things
like planning errors
by agents, which is when
its beliefs are right,
but it takes the wrong action.
So there's a clear
difference there,
which is important
to distinguish.
For example, like I said,
clicking a non-existent button
is hallucination, whereas
choosing a bad strategy
is a planning error.
So the takeaway is that
hallucination is not the same
as all types of model errors.
So why this definition
matters is that it
makes assumptions explicit.
So in the future, when people
talk about hallucination
or investigate things like
hallucination mitigation
techniques, they should define
what is the reference or ground
truth world model, what is
the view that the model sees,
and what is the conflict
resolution policy.
So this allows for better
comparisons across benchmarks,
consistent definitions,
and allows for assumptions
to be explicitly stated.
Furthermore, this also
enables the production
of scalable benchmarks.
So we're currently
working on an extension
to this paper,
which is producing
a benchmark of HalluWorld.
So by having a mathematical
grounded definition, what
it means is you can produce a
lot of examples of hallucination
through synthetic environments
by manipulating those three
different aspects
I talked about,
the reference world,
the view, as well as
the conflict resolution policy.
So again, having them
be explicitly defined
means you can mathematically
manipulate them
and as a result
construct a large scale
variety of different synthetic
hallucination examples.
So this can be used for
evaluating hallucination models,
as well as for training better
hallucination mitigation
techniques in the future.
So feel free to
check out our paper,
and our benchmark will
be released later on.
So in general, again,
we define hallucination
as incorrect world
modeling, which depends on
what is true, the ground
truth reference world, what
is seen by the model,
and how conflict should
be resolved by the model.
And the key
implications again, are
to reduce confusion
across papers
by making assumptions
explicit and allowing
for better evaluation benchmarks
and mitigation techniques.
Next, so we talked a lot--
well, Kart mentioned
briefly about things
like continual learning.
So I'll talk first
about long-term memory.
So a lot of current models
are still stateless,
as in there's no persistent
learning across interactions.
So what we want is some
way of storing information
across sessions.
Like the human brain, we're
able to remember things.
We have a memory system
built into our heads.
This allows us to retrieve
and reuse past experiences.
And we want a model
to be able to do that
as well to update its
knowledge over time.
This will allow it to
personalize and adapt
to different situations
as they change,
and as well as support things
like continual learning
and long horizon
reasoning and planning.
So today, a lot of
memory is stored
in things like external systems,
things like vector databases
and so forth that
we retrieve upon.
Sometimes what we do
is we simply summarize
past information and keep it as
compressed parts of the context.
We also use structured
memory, data structures,
things like lists,
graphs, and so forth.
And what is missing is more
reliable memory updating.
So when we have new
information that we
want to store into memory,
what if it contradicts
previous information?
What happens then?
Do we erase the
previous-- do we override
the previous information?
Do we store them as two
separate pieces of information
and so forth?
And when our memory gets
super long and large,
that is overwhelming, how do we
prune or get rid of past memory?
Which examples do we throw out?
The oldest ones, the ones
that are least important?
How do we define which ones are
most important and so forth?
So this relates to
something called
lifelong or continuous learning.
So ideally, we want AI
systems that can continuously
learn after deployment.
So after they're
trained, when they're
deployed into real world, when
they're interacting with users,
we want them to
learn, for example,
through implicit feedback
and real world interactions
and experiences.
And ideally, we want this to
be infinite and permanent.
We want it to update
the model weights, which
is analogous to the brain.
This is the brain of the model.
So a lot of the current
ways that models
learn at inference time is
it's inference time only.
It's context only, for example.
So this isn't permanent.
The brain or weights of
the model aren't updating.
This leads to the debate, which
I won't get too much into here,
which is do we truly
need parametric updates
to the weights of the model for
it to be continuously learning,
or is in-context
learning enough?
But I argue that true continual
learning should involve updates
to the brain or the
weights of the model?
And current work, a lot
of this involves things
like model distillation,
things, again, self-improvement
and reflection, which are
again inference only time
enhancements, not updating
the brain of the model.
So what mechanisms
or things do we
need to investigate to really
get to true, continual,
or lifelong learning
like humans?
Again as humans, I'm learning
continuously right now
just by talking to you,
giving this lecture.
I don't need to be sat
down in a chair every month
and have the whole
internet read to me.
I'm learning
continuously on the spot
without needing a
explicit fine tuning
process every once in a while.
So there's this concept
of model editing, which
tries to edit specific
nodes of the model,
for example, given new
facts or information.
They use this
thing, for example,
called Rank-One Model Editing
or ROME to modify model weights.
But this has a lot of
inherent weaknesses.
It really only works
for simple facts.
And furthermore, it cannot
easily propagate changes
to other related
or dependent facts.
For example, if I
update, for example,
saying Bob's dad is adjacent
to Bob's, that is Justin,
but Bob also has a
sister, the sister's dad
should also be updated.
But this propagation
isn't really possible
when it comes to model editing
because there could be hundreds,
for example, related facts
that must be updated,
which is not really possible
with this model editing
approach.
Now, other than continual
learning and lifelong learning,
which I think is a
key piece to AGI,
there's another disadvantage
or weakness of very large scale
models these days.
So millions or
billions or trillions
of parameters, language
models trained on tons of data
means they're effectively a
very large black boxes, which
are hard to understand
and interpret.
So there's a line of
work on interpretability,
which is trying to understand
exactly how these models learn
and think.
They understand their
internal representations,
what they truly think,
not just what they're
outputting or producing.
So mechanistic
interpretability has
a lot of techniques looking at
things like circuits as well
as features and related
parts of the model
to understand what exactly is
going on internally to unpack
this black box.
Furthermore, such large models
means they're very effective,
and they're going to be
used for many things that
interface with the real world.
But it's important
that they're aligned.
So they do what exactly
we intend them to do
and that they're safe.
So there's this
alignment problem,
especially as models get
very large and powerful.
There's a lot of issues
with existing models, which
is a lot of the times they take
shortcuts to achieve a goal,
and these shortcuts
might be unsafe or not
exactly what you want.
They might not be able to
generalize well to new domains
and settings, so they might
be aligned or trained well,
but deployed to a
different setting,
they might exhibit erratic or
unintended, unsafe behavior.
So some specific failure modes
are things reward-hacking.
So instead of optimizing
the true goal,
it finds some way
of just optimizing
the reward and, for example,
a way that is not good.
It could also learn to optimize
the hidden objectives which
might not be known to the
person training the model
or using the model.
Additionally, we talked a lot
about chain of thought reasoning
or long reasoning chains.
But how do we know that
the reasoning steps
that the model outputs
is truly what it
believes or is using to reason?
So this is called
a faithfulness.
So again, the explanations
that the model is producing
might be post-hoc
rather than what
is actually conditioned upon in
order to get the right answer.
So things like
causal interventions
are one way of actually
assessing faithfulness
of reasoning steps.
And like I said, there
might be distribution shifts
where behaviors might
change in new environments.
So some different
alignment techniques,
we touched upon these
human and AI feedback.
This allows the model to
learn from human preferences
to be safer and more aligned.
But again, things like RLHF
are prone to two failure
modes like reward-hacking.
So that's something
to investigate.
Again, I talked about
interpretability,
truly understand what
is going on, especially
internally within the model.
And I also mentioned
earlier process supervision.
So being able to
reward reasoning steps
and actually examine individual
steps of a model's reasoning
process is important, rather
than simply only looking
at its final
answers or outcomes.
Furthermore, so this idea of
constitutional AI, I believe,
was introduced by Anthropic.
So they actually give it a
constitution, a written document
with a lot of rules or
behavior or principles
to guide the model's behavior.
And they actually
use this in order
to post train the
model to get it to more
aligned with this constitution.
There's also this idea
of scalable oversight,
so having humans oversee
these models, which
might grow to become super
powerful and very large
in number is not feasible.
So what if we use models
to supervise other models?
So that's the idea of
scalable oversight.
And overall,
alignment, the goal is
to ensure models
pursue the right goals
and behave reliably under all
different types of conditions.
So lastly, I'll talk about
what comes after transformers.
So again, our course, again,
it's titled Transformers United.
But frankly, I think
it's a good idea
to think outside the box
to not all focus only
on transformers research, which
is what most people are doing
these days, but to think
about what else might
be interesting to investigate
because there's no guarantee
that transformers and
next token prediction
will lead to AGI or
superintelligence.
So again, transformers dominate,
but they have limitations,
things like inefficiencies,
especially scaling with larger
context and sequence
lengths, it is quadratic.
It fails a lot of times
with long context reasoning,
and it doesn't
really truly learn--
well, this is debatable.
But I believe as
well that it has
limitations in terms of truly
understanding the world.
It's not truly learning
an effective world model
in most cases.
So this leads to these
two emerging directions.
So the first are world models
and this thing proposed
by Yann LeCun called JEPA.
It moves beyond next
token prediction
to actually truly try to
learn how the world works.
So world models are basically
structured representations
of environments, again,
the actual world,
and it's about predicting
future states, not just tokens.
And this will enable things
like planning and reasoning
more effectively over
time that is also grounded
in how the actual world works.
So JEPA stands for Joint
Embedding Predictive
Architecture.
So instead of predicting raw
outputs like the next token,
it instead predicts
latent representations.
So this focuses on latent
structure rather than
explicit surface details
like tokens themselves.
And this avoids the
modeling of low level noise,
but actually looks at
the latent structure.
So this leads to more data
efficient learning, better
abstraction and generalization,
and is arguably closer
to how humans learn, which
is through predicting
structure and
states of the world
rather than simply
pixels or tokens.
Next, there's this
alternative architecture
being investigated
these days called
State Space Models or SSMs.
And instead of modeling
things like transformers
and instead model sequences
using continuous state updates,
maintaining a compressed
internal state over time.
So you'll see that this
is a bit analogous to how
Recurrent Neural
Networks or RNNs actually
work through a hidden state.
And this leads to
more efficiency.
It's linear time
scaling rather than
quadratic with the number
of tokens like transformers
and the attention mechanism.
So it's more effective
for long sequences,
and it has stronger performance
on longer context tasks.
And a specific example of this
is the Mamba architecture,
which is a selective
state space model.
However, SSMs do
carry trade offs.
They're less flexible than
attention in certain settings.
And this is still
an earlier area
of research, which is
being investigated.
So thank you for listening.
That is our presentation.
So we touched upon how
transformers work, the evolution
of things from word embeddings,
Word2Vec to things like RNNs,
transformers,
pre-training as well
as post-training, various
post-training techniques,
remaining challenges and
weaknesses, things still
remaining between us and AGI
or superintelligence, things
like continual learning, proper
alignment, interpretability,
and potentially state space
models as well as world models
instead.
So starting next week,
we'll have speakers come in
to give interesting talks
about what they're working on.
So actually, next week,
we'll have Hazel Nam,
who will be coming to talk
about her work on JEPA and world
models.
And the week after we'll
be having Albert Goo
talk about his work on Mamba
and state space machines.
So, ironically, our
first two speakers
will not be talking about
transformers, but alternative
architectures.
But I highly encourage you
guys to learn more and think
outside the box.
And please stay up-to-date
on our Discord mailing list.
And fill out the attendance
form starting next week.
And we'll see you
guys next Thursday.